Erwin F. Springweiler Papers
Erwin F. Springweiler Papers
1912-1967
Springweiler, Erwin F., 1896-1968
2 linear ft.
Spanning 1912 to 1967, the Erwin F. Springweiler Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the German American medalist and sculptor (1896-1968). The collection illuminates the professional career of the artist, who specialized in commemorative medals and animal sculpture. Includes letters from Archer Milton Huntington, Hazel Brill Jackson, Carl Paul Jennewein, Gertrude K. Lathrop, Paul Manship, A.A. Weinman, and Robert A. Weinman.
148685
Biographical History
Erwin F. Springweiler (1896-1968) was a German-born American medalist and sculptor, specializing in animals.
Born in Pforzheim, Germany, Springweiler trained at the Munich Academy and worked with the American sculptor Paul Manship in Havana, Cuba. During the 1930s, Springweiler was one of several artists sponsored by the Works Progress Administration (WPA), and create paintings for numerous post offices across the United States. His sculpture of an anteater stands in the National Zoological Park in Washington, D.C. [Biography adapted from information on the website of the Smithsonian American Art Museum.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Erwin F. Springweiler Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence-subject files, artwork, writings, and memorabilia.
Incoming letters, a few outgoing drafts, and a variety of related printed materials form the Correspondence-Subject Files. The collection includes letters from fellow sculptors Hazel Brill Jackson, C. Paul Jennewein, Gertrude K. Lathrop, Paul Manship, A. A. Weinman, and Robert A. Weinman. Organizational correspondence includes that of Brookgreen Gardens, the International Institute of Arts and Letters, the National Academy of Design, the National Sculpture Society, the R. W. Norton Art Gallery, the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and the Society of Medalists. Correspondence from the U. S. Treasury Department documents a number of Springweiler's most important sculpture commissions, including those for the National Zoological Park, the post office in Chester, Pennsylvania, and the 1939 New York World's Fair, as well as the production of his George M. Cohan Medal.
Artwork encompasses both original sketches and photographic or printed reproductions. Arranged by format, designs for medals and plaques, two sketchbooks, animal and human figure drawings, and a few miscellaneous, mostly mechanical, drawings constitute the original artwork. The organization of the photographic and printed reproductions of the completed medals and sculpture corresponds to the categorical arrangement of the original sketches.
Writings consists of two essays and some notes on art, the latter mainly in German.
Memorabilia is composed of photographs and printed material. Photographs include formal portraits of Springweiler as well as a number of images of the artist at work in his studio. Printed material includes certificates of award in school competitions from the Kunstgewerbeschule Pforzheim, clippings (1923-1955), and exhibition catalogs (1932-1960).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Artwork is divided into originals and reproductions, and listed alphabetically within each category. Writings and Memorabilia are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Huntington, Archer M. (Archer Milton), 1870-1955.; Jackson, Hazel Brill.; Jennewein, Carl Paul, 1890-1978.; Manship, Paul, 1885-1966.; Springweiler, Erwin F., 1896-1968.; Weinman, Adolph A. (Adolph Alexander), 1870-1952.; Weinman, Robert A.; Animal sculptors -- United States -- 20th century.; Animals in art.; Art, American -- 20th century.; German Americans.; Medalists -- United States.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Medalists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Erwin F. Springweiler, 1967-1971.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - American Academy of Achievement, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Brookgreen Gardens, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Franklin Mint, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Franklin-Institut Lindau, See International Institute of Arts and Letters
  - General Numismatics Corporation, See National Commemorative Society
  - Huntington, Archer Milton, See Brookgreen Gardens
  - International Institute of Arts and Letters, 1955-1957; undated (Box 1)
  - Jackson, Hazel Brill, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Jennewein, Carl Paul, See American Academy of Achievement
  - Lathrop, Gertrude K., 1941; undated (Box 1)
  - Manship, Paul, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Medallic Art Company, 1960; 1967 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Design, 1938; 1947-1949,; 1959,; 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - National Commemorative Society, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - National Sculpture Review, See National Sculpture Society
  - National Sculpture Society, 1942; 1955,; 1967 (Box 1)
  - New York World's Fair, 1939, See United States. Treasury Department
  - R. W. Norton Art Gallery (Shreveport, La.), 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1947; 1967 (Box 1)
  - Society of Medalists, 1941-1942; undated (Box 1)
  - United States. Air Force, 1948 (Box 1)
  - United States. Post Office, See United States. Treasury Department.
  - United States. Treasury Department, 1937-1947 (Box 1)
  - Weinman, Adolph Alexander, 1946-1947; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Weinman, Robert A., 1967 (Box 1)
  - A-Z, unidentified, 1937-1967 (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Original
    - Designs for medals and plaques, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Designs for medals and plaques, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Sketchbooks, undated; 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Sketches (Box 1)
      - Animals, undated (Box 1)
      - Animal, undated (Oversize 1)
      - Human figure, 1923; 1932-1935,; undated (Oversize 1)
      - Human figure, 1932; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Reproductions
    - Medals and plaques, undated (Box 2)
    - Sculpture
      - Animal, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Human figure, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Essays (2), undated; manuscript and galley proof (Box 2)
  - Notes on art, undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Printed material
    - Art Anatomy of Animals / Ernest E. Thompson, presentation copy to E. Springweiler from MacDowell Colony fellows (Oversize 2)
    - Certificates of award in school competitions, Kunstgewerbeschule Pforzheim, 1912-1916 (Box 2)
    - Certificates, National Academy of Design, National Sculpture Society, 1937; 1947,; 1958,; 1963,; 1967 (Oversize 1)
    - Clippings, 1923-1955; undated (Box 2)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1932-1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Map, Ravensteins Reise und Eisenbahnkarte von Deutschland (Box 2)
    - Periodical issue (with title page notes) Die Lehrer der Kunst + Werkschule Pforzheim 20 Jahrg., Heft 1/2, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Miscellany (Box 2)